<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:ddhi="http://ddhi.dartmouth.edu/ns"
    xml:lang="en">
    
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Oral History Interview: Onion Portage &amp; Noatak River</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Interviewer</resp>
                    <name>James Whitney</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Unpublished digital transcript, April 22 2025</p>
            </publicationStmt>
             
                <sourceDesc>
                <recordingStmt>
                    <recording type="video">
                        <date when="2000-01-01">January 01 2001</date>
                    </recording>
                </recordingStmt>
                <listPlace>
                    <place xml:id="onionPortage">
                        <placeName>Onion Portage</placeName>
                    </place>
                    <place xml:id="noatak">
                        <placeName>Noatak River</placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person xml:id="jw">
                    <persName>James Whitney</persName>
                    <note type="role">Interviewer</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="da">
                    <persName>Douglas Anderson</persName>
                    <note type="role">Interviewee</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="wa">
                    <persName>Wanni Anderson</persName>
                    <note type="role">Interviewee</note>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>
                    Encoded per TEI P5 + DDHI guidelines  
                    (<ref target="https://ddhi.dartmouth.edu/ddhi-encoding-guidelines">DDHI</ref>).
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="transcript" xml:id="transcript01">
                <head>Transcript of Interview</head>
                
                <u who="#da">
                    
                        At <placeName ref="onionPortage">Onion Portage</placeName>, when  
                        Giddings first started excavating there with a major expedition, which  
                        was in <date when="1964">1964</date>, after he had already gone back.  
                        And there’s a whole history of how he originally got to  
                        <placeName ref="#onionPortage">Onion Portage</placeName> and for the  
                        main expedition. But, the thing was in <date when="1964">1964</date>,  
                        that these three families, the <persName>Greist</persName>,  
                        <persName>Downey</persName>, and <persName>Lee</persName> would come,  
                        with their whole families—moved down and camped just below the main  
                        part of the archeological site. And so they were with their kids and all.  
                        It was an actual small village that was all for excavating. For  
                        <persName>Giddings</persName>, the thing was so ideal is that these excavators were older  
                        Iñupiat and knew so much because it was their lives. When they pulled up  
                        an object they’d say, “oh, yes, this is what it is,” give the Iñupiat  
                        word for it, and explain how we use it. Because it was remote—it was  
                        close enough to what they’d experienced. It was really their living  
                        remembering of objects and so it was very useful that way. The Iñupiat  
                        excavators were expert, so easy for <persName>Giddings</persName> to say, “okay, this is  
                        where we’ll excavate, this is what we’re going to do,” and then turn it  
                        over to them to excavate. And it worked out really well.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#da">
                    
                        And then in <date when="1964">1964</date> I joined the expedition. I was  
                        at the <orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName> as a student, and  
                        joined the crew at <placeName ref="#onionPortage">Onion Portage</placeName>  
                        before going up to the <placeName ref="#noatak">Noatak River</placeName>  
                        for my own doctoral research. I spent the first part of the summer at  
                        <placeName ref="#onion Portage">Onion Portage</placeName>, got to know  
                        all the families really well, excavated there before I went on to the  
                        Noatak. Then after that field season, in September–October, after  
                        Giddings had returned to <orgName>Brown University</orgName>, that was  
                        when he had his <eventName>car accident</eventName> that ended up killing him.  
                        That happened in <date when="1964-11">November 1964</date> (or maybe  
                        early December). I was back at <orgName>Penn</orgName> doing classwork  
                        when I was asked to come up. The question was that the  
                        <placeName ref="#onionPortage">Onion Portage</placeName> expedition  
                        had hit the archaeological news because it was a stratified site. As you  
                        know, work in the <placeName>Arctic</placeName> rarely finds stratified  
                        sites—soil formation is minimal. Usually everything is on the surface or  
                        sod level, so 10 000 years might be in a very thin sod layer.  
                        <placeName ref="#onionPortage">Onion Portage</placeName> was different:  
                        for geological reasons it was nearly five meters deep and stratified—  
                        it really was amazing. So everyone knew about it.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#da">
                    
                        When Giddings died—he had an <eventName>NSF grant</eventName> to continue the  
                        expedition—but after his accident he worried he wouldn’t recover for the  
                        next summer. He said, “to have continuity, let a student of mine at  
                        Penn—me—take over until I recover.” Then he died. The university  
                        negotiated with my professor <persName>Froelich Rainey</persName> (a  
                        close friend since the <date>1930s</date> at the <orgName>University of Alaska</orgName>).  
                        They arranged for <persName>Rainey</persName> to be the project director,  
                        with me as field director. <persName>Rainey</persName> was appointed by  
                        <orgName>Brown University</orgName> as a visiting professor for <date>1965</date>,  
                        and I became field director.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#da">
                    
                        That’s how I first took over at <placeName ref="#onionPortage">Onion Portage</placeName>.  
                        It was the same crew—the <persName>Lees</persName>, the  
                        <persName>Greist</persName>, and the <persName>Downeys</persName>. They’d  
                        wintered in Ambler, then moved back down to Onion Portage each summer.  
                        That was the <date>1965</date> season—my original season.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#da">
                    
                        I had three students from Brown: two later earned PhDs in archaeology—  
                        <persName>Clifford Hickey</persName> (later director of the <orgName>Boreal  
                        Institute, Univ. of Alberta</orgName>) and <persName>David Wyatt</persName>  
                        (taught in British Columbia). From then on, all material was packed in  
                        Alaska and shipped back to the <orgName>Haffenreffer Museum of Anthropology</orgName>  
                        for analysis—procedure continues for years.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#jw">
                    
                        Yeah, that’s a great introduction to what I was interested in—families  
                        and the whole scene at <placeName ref="#onionPortage">Onion Portage</placeName>.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#da">
                    Yes.
                </u>
                
                <u who="#jw">
                    
                        So, Wanni, maybe you want to introduce yourself. Was it 1965 your first  
                        season?
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#wa">
                    Yes.
                </u>
                
                <u who="#jw">
                    To <placeName ref="#onionPortage">Onion Portage</placeName>? Talk about how you came in.
                </u>
                
                <u who="#da">
                    No, ’66.
                </u>
                
                <u who="#wa">
                    ’66.
                </u>
                
                <u who="#jw">
                    Okay, so talk about your first time up in Alaska.
                </u>
                
                <u who="#wa">
                    
                        I got involved through Doug’s work. My first field season was <date>1966</date>; I  
                        was still at the <orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName>. It was  
                        just beginning to interest me—folklore and anthropology. Joining that  
                        expedition gave me ethnographic experience, foundation for my  
                        dissertation in <placeName>Thailand</placeName>. I served as field  
                        assistant. My first year was rough—coming from Thailand I’d never  
                        camped. Fortunately, <persName>Betts Giddings</persName> (Dr. Giddings’  
                        wife) helped me learn camp life: she pitched her tent by the cabin on  
                        the hill above the excavation, and I set mine next to hers. The crew  
                        camped closer to the river.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#wa">
                    
                        My responsibility was to assist excavation half‑days—usually digging  
                        beside Betts to learn her method. Sometimes crew members invited me to  
                        dig with them—they said, “Wanni, come dig here; you might find  
                        something exciting.” That built rapport with the crew and students.  
                        We took a break at <eventName>Kool‑Aid time</eventName> around 10:30 am (Betts  
                        made <eventName>Kool‑Aid</eventName>; I assisted), and another around 3 pm. We dug until 5 pm.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#da">
                    Yeah.
                </u>
                
                <u who="#wa">
                    
                        Our work hours were 9 am to 5 pm. For cooking, <persName>Clara Lee</persName>  
                        (wife of <persName>Tommy Lee</persName>) was our cook; her daughter  
                        <persName>Helena Lee</persName> assisted early on, later joined by  
                        <persName>Myra Lee</persName> and <persName>Alice Lee</persName>. We  
                        had a close connection with the Lee family, camping near the river.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#wa">
                    
                        Doug began training me in anthropology—I worked with the women: fish  
                        netting and drying fish, photographing them. <persName>Clara Lee</persName>  
                        was a skilled skin‑clothing stitcher. We commissioned mukluks and parkas  
                        from her when planning winter fieldwork in  
                        <placeName>Selawik</placeName>. She noted Selawik had the best  
                        <eventName>muskrat trapping</eventName>. We bought 60–70 muskrat skins, she  
                        made women’s parkas (belly fur) and men’s parkas (backbone fur). Those  
                        parkas remain part of the <orgName>Haffenreffer Museum</orgName>  
                        collection.
                    
                </u>
                
                <u who="#wa">
                    
                        That’s how we stayed warm in <placeName>Selawik</placeName>; those garments are still in the  
                        <orgName>Haffenreffer Museum</orgName>.
                    
                </u>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>


